A Finding Aid to the Florence Allen Papers, 1920-1997, in the Archives of American Art AAA.alleflor
Archives of American Art
Florence Allen papers
1920-1997
AAA.alleflor
Archives of American Art
0.5 Linear feet
The collection measures 0.5 linear feet, dates from 1920 to 1997, and documents the career of artist's model Florence Allen. Found within the papers are biographical material, letters, notes and writings, art work, and printed material. Of particular interest are a wide variety of photographs, including 19th century photographs of Allen family members, photographs of Florence Allen posing for artists, socializing with famous friends such as Paul Robeson, Harry Belefonte, Paul Newman, Allen Ginsberg, and participating in protest marches. There is also an autographed photo of Bob Hope.
Allen, Florence W. (Florence Wysinger), 1913-1997
Biographical Note
Florence Wysinger Allen was born in Oakland, California, in 1913, the granddaughter of early African-American settlers. Her mother, née Moore, was a concert pianist, and her father, Arthur, as a boy in 1892, was named in the case of Wysinger vs. Crookshank which led to the desegregation of schools in California.
Florence Allen was educated at Fremont High School and later became involved in the San Francisco literary and artistic community as a civil rights activist and newspaper columnist. She began modeling in 1933 and worked as an artist's model for most of the prominent figurative painters working in the Bay Area of San Francisco, including Diego Rivera, Mark Rothko, and Wayne Thiebaud. She also worked as a model in university art classes, including those at the San Francisco Art Institute, Mills College, University of California at Berkeley, Stanford University, and the California College of Arts and Crafts.
In 1945, Ms. Allen founded the San Francisco Models' Guild. After injuries from a traffic accident limited her mobility in 1987, she became the Model Coordinator at the College of Arts and Crafts in Oakland where she also taught a Model Certification Workshop.
Florence Allen died June 1, 1997 in El Sobrante, California.
Scope and Content Note
The papers of artist's model Florence Allen measure 0.5 linear feet and date from 1920-1997. Found within the papers are biographical material, scattered letters that generally discuss some of Allen's activities, miscellaneous notes and writings, a drawing and a silhouette, and clippings. The primary value of this collection rests in its wide variety of photographs. As well as 19th century photographs of Allen family members the collection contains photographs of Florence Allen posing for artists, socializing with famous friends such as Paul Robeson, Harry Belefonte, Paul Newman and Allen Ginsberg, and participating in protest marches. There is also an autographed photo of Bob Hope.
Provenance
The Florence Allen papers were donated in 1995 and 1999 by Florence Allen via Austin Conkey, an informal executor, who maintained Allen's papers.
Restrictions on Access
The collection is open for research. Use requires an appointment.
Belafonte, Harry, 1927- -- Photographs; Newman, Paul, 1925- -- Photographs; Artists' models--California--San Francisco; Photographs
- Florence Allen Papers, 1942-1947; Series 1; 0.4 Linear feet Box 1
  Scope and Contents note
  The series contains biographical material, scattered letters that generally discuss some of Allen's activities, miscellaneous notes and writings, a drawing and a silhouette, clippings, and a wide variety of photographs. In addition to 19th century photographs of Allen family members, the series includes photographs of Florence Allen posing for artists, socializing with famous friends such as Paul Robeson, Harry Belefonte, Paul Newman and Allen Ginsberg, and participating in protest marches. There is also an autographed photo of Bob Hope.
  - Diploma, 1942 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Constitution and By-Laws of the San Francisco Models' Guild and Dues Book, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Letters, 1962-1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 3-6)
  - Typescript "A Short History of the Visalia Colored School" By Mervyn G. Shippey, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Miscellaneous Notes and Writings, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Cut-out Silhouette Portrait and a Drawing, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Clippings, 1945-1997, undated (Box 1, Folder 10-13)
  - Autographed Brochure for Actor, Scott Beach, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Photographs of Family Members, undated (Box 1, Folder 15-21)
  - Photographs of Florence Allen, 1920-1987 (Box 1, Folder 22-35)
    See also OV 2.
  - Photographs of Allen's Friends, undated (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
  - Photographs of Portrait Busts and View of a Garden, undated (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Oversized Photographs of Family Members and Florence Allen, undated (Box OV 2)